Let's consider some process models for
自動運転車が高速道路に合流しようとしている状況の
a situation where a self-driving car is trying to merge onto a highway.
プロセスモデルについて考えてみましょう
But, let's say there is another vehicle in the rightmost lane.
よく見ると、別の車が右端の車線を走行しています
Now, this vehicle might do a few things.
この車は合流しようとしている車を
It might just ignore us,
無視してそのまま走行する
it might speed up to let us merge behind it,
加速して後方に合流スペースを作る
it might slow down to let us get ahead of it,
減速して前方に合流スペースを作る
or it might change lanes.
車線変更するといった場合が考えられます
Now, for each of these behaviors,
そこで、各ケースのプロセスモデルを
we want to come up with a process model that formalizes the likely motion of the car.
作成して予測される動きを正規化してみましょう
If the car ignores us,
無視してそのまま走行する場合
it will likely follow lane A with constant velocity.
一定速度で車線 A を追従すると考えられます
If they speed up, we may choose to model
加速する場合は正の値の加速度で
their motion as lane following with positive acceleration.
車線を追従するモーションモデルになるでしょう
If they slow down,
減速も同様ですが
we would do the same thing,
この場合は加速度が
but with negative acceleration.
負の値となります
Lane changing, we could model as lane following on lane B, with constant velocity.
車線変更には、車線 B を一定速度で追従するモデルを使用します
You can see this term lane following show up a lot.
ここで、追従という用語が何度か登場しましたが
What is lane following?
車線追従とは何のことでしょうか
How do we describe it mathematically?
数学的にはどう表現できるでしょうか
We have many options here.
これには多くの選択肢があります
In general, there is a tradeoff between
通常、プロセスモデルを選択する際には
simplicity and accuracy when choosing a process model.
簡潔性と精度のトレードオフを考慮しなければなりません
One very simple approach is to treat
非常にシンプルなアプローチの 1 つに
the car as a point particle with holonomic properties.
車両をホロノミックな点粒子として扱う方法があります
This means we assume the point can move in any direction at any time.
その場合、点は随時あらゆる方向に動く可能性があると考えます
Which of course is a very simplistic assumption.
もちろん、これは大変シンプルな想定で
The simplest motion models are linear.
最も単純なモーションモデルは線形になります
Constant velocity lane following for any coordinates would look something like this.
一定速度での車線追従はどの座標であっても、このような式になります
Where the car moves forward at each timestep,
車両は各タイムステップにおいて前進し
and is assumed to keep a constant distance to the lane center.
車線中心との距離が一定に保たれていると仮定しています
In practice, linear point models usually wind up being too simplistic.
しかし実際には、線形モデルでは単純すぎます
The next step in complexity happens when we allow non-linearities into our model.
そこでより複雑にするため、モデルに非線形的な要素を加えます
Typically, if you start incorporating heading into our state vector,
通常、状態ベクトルに見出しを組み込むと
you will end up with sines and cosines in our model equations.
モデルの方程式でサインとコサインを使うことになります
An example of a non-linear point model of lane
車線追従の非線形モデルは、デカルト座標では
following could look like this in Cartesian coordinates.
このような式になる可能性があります
Note the presence of cosine and sine,
ご覧のとおり、サインとコサインがありますね
which are where the non-linearity comes in.
これが非線形の要素です
The next jump in complexity happens when we
次に、車両は非ホロノミックシステムであると
take into account that a car is a non-holonomic system.
いう点を考慮するとより複雑化します
A popular approach is to use a bicycle model,
そこでよく使用されるのが自転車モデルで
which looks like this in an inertial cartesian reference frame.
慣性デカルト座標系ではこのようになります
A bicycle model takes two inputs,
自転車モデルはステアリング角度と
the steering angle and the acceleration.
加速の 2 つの入力を取得します
For the steering angle,
ステアリング角度に関しては
we could use a PID controller with the target lane center line as the reference line.
目標車線の中心線を基準トラジェクトリーとして PID コントローラーを使用できます
For the acceleration, we could once again use a constant velocity model,
加速には一定速度モデルまたは一定加速モデルを使用し
or a constant acceleration model,
より複雑な加速挙動を扱いたい場合は
or if we wanted more complex acceleration behavior,
制限速度をターゲットとして
we could use a PID controller with the speed limit as the target.
PID コントローラーを使用します
In practice, these sorts of models tend to
実際のところ、これらのモデルは
strike a good balance between simplicity and accuracy.
簡潔性と精度のバランスがよく取れていますが
But you could always go more complex by including more details about vehicle dynamics.
車両力学に関する詳細を追加すれば、さらに複雑にすることも可能です
For example, you could use a dynamic bicycle model,
たとえば、このような動的自転車モデルを
which looks like this.
使用することができます
Note the presence of terms like F_c, f,
ここで、F_c, f は
which represents the lateral force on the tires at the front of the vehicle,
前輪にかかる横方向の力
and F_c, r, which represents the lateral force on the rear tire.
F_c, r は後輪にかかる横方向の力を示しています
You could even add more complexity and model the four wheels of the car.
これをさらに複雑にして、4 本の車輪をモデル化することも可能です
While these models are technically more accurate than any of the others,
これらのモデルは他のモデルよりも技術的に正確ですが
in practice, using them doesn't usually make sense for prediction.
通常、実際の予測にはあまり適していません
There is so much uncertainty inherent to predicting the behaviors of other drivers that
他のドライバーの挙動は不確定要素が多すぎるため予測が難しく
minor accuracy improvements to process models just
プロセスモデルの精度を多少改善したところでさほど意味がなく
aren't worth the computational overhead that they come with.
計算負荷に見合う価値がないと言えるでしょう
Note how all the models contain an additional term
どのモデルにも W という用語が使われていますが
W. This is where the uncertainty on the process model is stored.
これはプロセスモデルの不確実性が格納されている場所です
A classic choice to represent uncertainty is a multivariate Gaussian with zero mean.
不確実性を示す際には、平均値 0 の多変量ガウス分布を使うのが最も一般的です
Next, I'm going to ask you to think a bit more about process models.
次に、プロセスモデルについてもう少し考察し
Then, we will talk about how we can reason about
複数のプロセスモデルを同時に検討して
multiple behaviors by considering multiple process models simultaneously.
複数の挙動について結論を下すにはどうすればよいか考えしましょう